Hi, welcome back! In previous videos we've looked at
स्वागत है | पिछले वीडियो में हमने देखा था
pivot tables extensively, and in the previous video
pivot tables, और पिछले वीडियो में हमने देखा था
we looked at how to use different functions: like an AVERAGE function
कैसे इस्तेमाल करना है अलग तरह के कार्य : जैसे AVERAGE कार्य
instead of a SUM.
SUM के अलावा |
And there's one more function that I'd really like to talk about and this
और एक कार्य है जिसके बारे में मैं बात करना चाहूँगी और इसे
is called the Distinct Count.
Distinct Count  कहते है |
So it's different from a COUNTIF or a normal COUNT function, where you just
तो यह अलग है COUNTIF या एक मामूली से COUNT कार्य से , जहा पे आप बस
count the number of lines. This distinct count
गिनते है कितने लाइन्स है | यह distinct count
counts the number of different customers, in this case,
गिनता है कितने अलग अलग ग्राहक है , इस हिसाब से
that have bought a specific beer. So if you use a distinct count, you can see
एक तरह का बियर जो आपने खरीदा है | तो अगर आप distinct count इस्तेमाल करते है , आप देख सकते है
what beer is popular with a lot of different people.
कौनसा बियर सबसे ज़्यादा पसंदीदा है लोगो के बीच |
And that's really a different measure from a COUNT and in the exercises
और यह बहुत ही अलग है COUNT से और इन एक्सर्साइज़स में
we will talk about this distinct count a little bit more, so this is why I
हम बात करेंगे distinct count के बारे में , तो इसीलिय
wanted to show it to you.
मैं आपको दिखाना चाहती हूँ |
But there's one thing in the whole pivot table view
पर एक चीज़ है इस पूरे pivot table में
that we haven't really looked at yet, and that's this 'Columns', right here.
जो हमने अभी तक देखा नही है , और यह है 'Columns', ठीक यही पे |
So we filtered, we have used different functions, different values,
तो हमने छाँटा, हमने अलग अलग कार्य इस्तेमाल किया, अलग वॅल्यूस,
but we haven't added columns to the mix. And columns in a pivot table
पर हमने अभी तक कॉलम्स जोड़ा नही है | और कॉलम्स  pivot table में
literally add another dimension to your data analysis.
सचमुच एक और आयाम जोड़ता है आपके डेटा अनॅलिसिस के लिए |
Because, in previous videos, we've only looked at this row dimension
क्यूंकी , पिछले वीडियो में, हमने बस देखा है इस रो आयाम को
and now we're also going to add columns in our pivot table.
और अभी हम कॉलम्स जोड़ने वाले है हमारे pivot table में |
So let's have a look at how that goes. We don't need the guest ID
तो चलिए देखते है यह कैसे होता है | हमे इस गेस्ट ID की
and the count anymore. What we are going to add
और यह गणना की ज़रूरत नही है  | जो हम जोड़ने वाले है
as rows is all the different times and what we're going to add
रोस के तरह वो है सारे अलग समय और जो हम जोड़ने वाले है
as the calculation is
हिसाब के तरह है वो है
the count of the quantity. So what we see now,
गणना मात्रा| तो जो अभी हम देखते है वो हैं,
per time of the day: how many quantities have we sold?
हर दिन के एक समय पे : कितने मात्रा मे हमने बेचा है?
And then we drag in columns. So we add the guest IDs
और फिर हम इस कॉलम्स को नीचे खिचते है | तो हम जोड़ते है गेस्ट ID को
as columns. Let's zoom out a little bit so we can
कॉलम्स के तरह | चलिए और थोड़ा पीछे जाते है ताकि हम जान सके
better see what happens. So what we see now is an overview of
क्या हुआ अच्छे से | तो जो हम अभी देखते है वो है निरीक्षण
per customer at the time of the day what
हर एक ग्राहक का की किस समय पे क्या
is actually being sold. So you can see this first customer right here,
खरीदा गया था | तो आप देख सकते है यह पहला ग्राहक इधर ,
he is a regular. He buys beers at 5 p.m., at 7 p.m.
जो नियमित है | यह एक बियर खरीदते है 5 p.m को और 7 p.m को |
Whereas the second customers is different, he either buys before dinner
जबकि यह दूसरा ग्राहक अलग है यह या तो खाने से पहले खरीदते है या फिर
or after dinner. And the third customer again is different, because he only comes in
खाना खाने के बाद | और यह तीसरा ग्राहक भी अलग है, क्यूंकी यह सिर्फ़ आते है
late at night. And by analysing your data in this way you really
आधी रात को | और आप अपने डेटा आनलाइज़ करने के बाद इस तरह से
get an overview of what exactly happened, what times,
आपको एक अच्छा सा निरीक्षण मिलता है  की क्या होता है असलियत मे, कितने बजे
what customers are doing what? So this is not really
हमारे ग्राहक क्या कर रहे है ? तो यह असलियत में
meant for having an overview analysis, it is meant for really diving into
नही बना सिर्फ़ निरीक्षण करने, यह बना है अपने डेटा में डूब जाने के लिए
your data. So you can exactly see
तो आप अच्छे से देख सकते है
who is buying what at what time. So let's add another example of
कौन क्या खरीदता है कितने बजे | तो चलिए और एक उधारण जोड़ते है
using columns, so instead of using guest IDs we're now going to use
कॉलम्स का इस्तेमाल करके, तो गेस्ट ID के अलावा हम इस्तेमाल करने वाले है
beer IDs
बियर ID का
but we're keeping time as rows. So now we come profile beers.
और समय को रोस के तरह | तो हम अभी बियर्स के तरफ देखेंगे |
We see that this first beer right here, is really a beer
तो हम यह पहला बियर देखते है , यह एक बियर है
for early in the evening, where our second beer is a beer
जो शाम को लिया जाता है , जबकी यह दूसरा बियर एक बियर है
that's been sold late at night more. So by
जो बेचा जाता है आधी रात को | तो
adding columns to your pivot table you're not summarizing anymore,
columns जोड़के pivot table में आप सारांश नही कर रहे है
it's more like profiling what exactly happens in our data.
यह है क्या असलियत मे हो रहा है हमारे डेटा में |
And this, again, allows you to really gain a more detailed understanding
और यह फिर से आपको मौका देता है , और थोड़ा समझने
of what is happening in your data.
क्या हो रहा है आपके डेटा में |